Please support our work over
at Patreon.com/ProjectCensored
Thanks everyone for joining us back
at the Project Censored radio show.
We're very glad right now to be joined
by John Kiriakou, who is a former
CIA counterterrorism officer and a
former senior investigator with the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
John became the sixth whistleblower
indicted by the Obama administration
under the Espionage Act, a
law designed to punish spies.
He served 23 months in prison as
a result of his attempts to oppose
and blow the whistle on the Bush
administration's torture program.
John, thank you so much for joining us.
Thanks for having me, Eleanor.
Happy to do it.
So, starting off here, I want, because
you and Assange have this in common,
that you're both being pummeled by the
Espionage Act, and he would, like you,
end up in the Eastern District Court
of Virginia, and I was wondering if you
could give folks some context of what
that means to be in the Eastern District
Court, and how that flies in the face
of the argument that were Assange to be
extradited, he would receive a fair trial.
Oh, yeah.
First of all, bottom line up front.
It's not possible for him to
receive a fair trial in the
Eastern District of Virginia.
It's just not possible.
The easiest reason for that is that his
jury would be made up of people who work
for or who have friends or relatives
who work for the CIA, the Pentagon,
the Department of Homeland Security,
or any number of dozens and dozens of
intelligence community contractors.
That's the jury pool.
So it's just not possible
to, to get a fair trial.
And I'm going to ask
a rhetorical question.
You know, I was charged in the
Eastern District of Virginia.
Jeffrey Sterling, the CIA whistleblower,
was in the Eastern District.
Snowden has been charged in the
Eastern District, as has Julian.
But when former CIA Director David
Petraeus exposed the names of 10 covert
CIA operatives to his girlfriend, and
gave her access to the president's
black books, which were the most highly
classified documents that exist in the
American government, where was he charged?
He was charged in the Western
district of North Carolina.
They knocked his charge
down to a misdemeanor.
He took a plea and he got 18
months of unsupervised probation.
He kept his security clearance.
He kept his contract with the white house.
And at his sentencing hearing, the
judge came down from the bench to
shake his hand and to thank him
for his service to the country.
So there's a big difference in the
way people are treated under the
Espionage Act, depending on which
federal district you're charged in.
They call the Eastern District of
Virginia the Espionage Court for a reason.
And it's that no national security
defendant has ever won a case there.
Ever.
And I'm curious, too, because in
your trial, as I understand it, and
I'm hoping you can speak more to
this, you weren't actually allowed
to put up a defense for yourself.
No.
That's, that's one of the
quirks of the Espionage Act.
There is no affirmative defense.
You can't say, yes, I blew the whistle
on the CIA's torture program, but I did
it because it was an illegal program.
All you can say is, yes, I
exposed classified information.
You can't, you're forbidden
from saying why you did it.
And Ed Snowden, I was in close
touch with Ed Snowden after
he first made his revelations.
Well, first of all, he said he was
willing to come home and face the music.
And I said, listen, you've got to hire
the best lawyers that money can buy.
You should hire my lawyers, right?
And so he did, he hired my lawyers and
they immediately engaged in conversations
with the justice department to try to
work out a deal because as I said, he was
willing to come home and face the music
and go to prison, he told me this himself.
If they would allow him to stand up in
court to explain why he did what he did.
And they said, absolutely not.
So for whatever reason, that's never
been explained, it was better for the
justice department for Ed Snowden to make
a new life for himself in Russia than
it was for him to come back and explain
that the CIA and NSA and myriad other
services are spying on American citizens.
They wouldn't do it.
And it's really, I mean, if
you think about it, intention
is really a big deal in court.
Because it separates, of
course, murder trials.
Like, did you mean to kill the person,
or did you accidentally kill them?
So intention is really a vital
point of the justice system.
But not in the Espionage Act.
My lawyers actually tried to make that
argument in the very first hearing
that we had and, my judge, Judge Leonie
Brinkman, a Reagan appointee, she
interrupted the lawyers and she said,
I'm not going to respect precedent
from other courts  that the defendant
had to have a criminal intent.
And my lawyers are saying, well, wait a
minute, your honor, are you saying that a
person can accidentally commit espionage?
And she said, that's
exactly what I'm saying.
And then she turned to
me and she said, Mr.
Kiriakou, you either did
it or you didn't do it.
And I think you did it.
And that was it.
We blocked off three days.
We wrote up hundreds of
motions to throw out documents.
And we blocked off three days for
her to hear these 200 motions.
So we walked in.
And they were all about
criminal intent, right?
Because they showed, these cables
showed my refusal to take part in
the torture training, my objection
to torture while I was still in the
CIA, and there were dozens, hundreds
of cables that laid out the actual
torture techniques that were being used.
And she said, we walked into the
courtroom, and she said, I'm going
to save everybody a lot of time, and
I'm denying all 200 of these motions.
And so, that was it.
She declared us in recess and as
we were walking out, I said to my
lead attorney, what just happened?
And he said, we just lost the case.
That's what happened.
And that's the Eastern
District of Virginia.
In the end I got a best and final
offer from the Justice Department
and I decided to turn it down.
My wife and I stayed up all night talking
about what to do and I believed in my
heart that I was innocent and I was going
to turn it down and I said very naively,
once I get in front of a jury and I
explain what happened, they're going to
see how ridiculous these charges are.
So I emailed my attorneys very early
in the morning and they responded
immediately that three of them were
coming over to the house, four of
them were coming over to the house.
The one who was the oldest and the
most grizzled when he walked in, he
said to me, these were his exact words.
He said, you stupid son
of a bitch, take the deal.
And then the second one who was kind
of this Southern gentleman, he said,
listen, if you were my own brother,
I would beg you to take this deal.
It's not going to get
any better than this.
And then the third one who was
tough but who I liked and respected
the most got right in my face.
And forgive me if I've told this story too
many times, but got right in my face and
he said, you know what your problem is,
your problem is you think this is about
justice and it's not about justice, it's
about mitigating damage, take the deal.
And so I took the deal.
And that's what they expect.
That's why, according to ProPublica,
the federal government wins 98.
2 percent of its cases and in the Eastern
District of Virginia, they win 99.
1 percent of their cases.
You don't have a chance.
You can't win.
And as you've said before, Julian
Assange would not, I mean, there's no
way that he would be offered a deal by
the Justice Department at this point.
I doubt it.
The only way I could see the Justice
Department offering him a deal would
be if he or if Wikileaks had additional
information that had not yet been
released and as part of the deal,
they would negotiate, you know, X
amount of time in exchange for you
not releasing the information or
returning it back to the government.
But no, he's facing 175 years in
prison on dozens of espionage charges.
I can't imagine that they would want
to make that any easier for him.
And in your experience too, it's
not just about the Eastern District,
it's also about trying to ensure that
lives are destroyed after the fact.
And I was wondering if you could
share a little bit about that.
So  let's say that
somehow he was pardoned.
There's also this large state
apparatus that tries to ensure that
whistleblowers and truth tellers
have their lives destroyed even
outside of the justice system.
Yeah, you know, automatically
people walk away from you, right?
Friends, former colleagues, even
relatives will just walk away from you
and they'll never speak to you again.
That's hurtful, right?
But you can live with that.
Okay, you get to see who your
friends really were anyway.
And then you make new
friends in a new community.
So you're okay there.
But where you're not okay is you will
never work in your field ever again.
And on top of never working in
your field, you have a national
security felony conviction.
So you lose your federal pension.
You lose the right to vote.
You lose the right to ever own a firearm.
You're always a suspect in something.
I mean, it was years after I got
home from prison that the FBI
continued to follow me around.
Not all the time, but
with some regularity.
And so, here, myself as an
example, I was one of the U.S.
government's leading
experts on the Middle East.
And I ended up stocking shelves at
Michael's craft store on midnight
shift before I got a minimum wage
job at a left wing think tank,
and then finally my wife left.
She couldn't take it anymore.
So, that's all part of the
longer term punishment.
They want you to be ruined.
Not because they specifically
have it out for you, right?
They're not sitting around a table
saying, how can we screw Eleanor?
How can we make it so
she never works again?
What they're doing though is saying,
how can we use Eleanor as an example?
Where we make her so hurt that
other people are going to look
at her and say, you know, I was
thinking about blowing the whistle,
but look what they did to Eleanor.
I better keep my mouth shut.
A New York Times reporter told me that
on the day of my arrest, literally
every one of the New York Times
national security sources went silent
and stayed silent for six months.
And that was the goal.
That's what they wanted to do.
Wow, that is terrifying.
Well, and I'm curious too, because
you worked at the CIA, and because
the CIA has been particularly rabid
against Julian Assange, were you
surprised when you heard, for instance,
that Pompeo had hatched this plan
to have Julian Assange murdered?
Did that seem in step and in line with
how the CIA operates on the inside?
Yes.
And I'll tell you why.
I was sickened, of course, by this report.
You're talking about the
report from Yahoo News.
I was sickened by it,
but not at all surprised.
And there are a couple of little details
in there that are not generally publicly
known that I think are very important.
So what you're talking about is a report
by Michael Isikoff that ran in Yahoo News.
Now, Mike Isikoff is a very well
known, very highly respected national
security journalist here in Washington.
He's a Pulitzer Prize winner, made
his made his bones at Newsweek when
Newsweek was a major publication.
He was able to get 30 current
and former intelligence officers
to talk to him for this report.
So it's not like just one guy said, Oh,
Pompeo wanted to kill Julian Assange.
This is 30 people from the inside who
gave the details of this operation.
Now the idea was if Julian attempted
to leave the Ecuadorian embassy that
he would be snatched off the street
and rendered, either to the Eastern
District of Virginia to face trial,
or to Guantanamo to be held until they
could figure out what to do with him.
Or, if they couldn't render him,
to shoot him dead in the street.
They also talked about a Plan C: that if
he were somehow to make his way to one
of London's airports and board a Russian
embassy flight, the CIA was authorized
to shoot out the tires of the plane.
Now this is an act of war, to
shoot out the tires of the plane to
ensure that it couldn't take off.
Okay, one of the things that most
people missed was a couple of days
before this became public, Mike Pompeo,
in an interview, called WikiLeaks a
hostile, non state intelligence service.
Those words were very carefully
chosen, because if WikiLeaks is a
hostile, non state, intelligence
service, that makes this whole
case a counterintelligence case.
Now, a counterintelligence
case would be run by the CIA's
counterintelligence center.
But counterintelligence cases
are the most highly classified
cases that the CIA handles.
They're so highly classified that
they are the only cases that don't
have to be briefed to the House
and Senate oversight committees.
Why?
Because counterintelligence usually
means that you're working for a
foreign power, a foreign government.
Well, if the CIA is investigating
a mole, who's to say that the mole
maybe isn't the chairman of the
Senate Intelligence Committee, right?
Or the ranking member of the
House Intelligence Committee.
So those are all held internally.
Well, if this operation were to be
carried out, all anybody would know
was that Julian Assange tried to leave
the embassy, the Ecuadorian embassy in
London, and he was shot dead, period.
And that's the end of the story.
That's why he used those very specific
words, that very specific term, or
terminology, that it was a hostile
non state intelligence service.
And of course it's not.
It's a transparency and journalism
outlet, but that's what they
don't want people to think.
And let me add one thing, and
this is just an educated guess.
I don't have any inside information to
prove that this is the case, but I think
the reason why this never happened was
the modus operandi for a covert action
program like this is you first go to
the CIA's general counsel, they say,
yes, it's legal, no, it's not legal.
If it's legal, it goes to the Justice
Department's Office of Legal Counsel,
OLC, and they say, yes, it's legal.
No, it's not legal.
If they say, then it goes to the National
Security Council General Counsel and
he'll say yes, it's legal, no, it's not.
If it is, it goes to the national
security advisor for a signature.
If that person signs it, it goes
to the president for his signature.
And if the president signs
it, it's implemented.
I think that it made its way to the N.S.C.
And I think the national security
advisor received it and said,
are they out of their minds?
We are going to assassinate a
Five Eyes citizen, a citizen of
Australia, who has never faced
his accusers in a court of law?
We're gonna murder him in broad daylight
in the street in Knightsbridge, London?
So somebody, probably the National
Security Advisor, was the adult
in the room and killed it.
But I think at the same time, there
were enough people in the CIA who
were aware of the planning for it
that they said, this is above and
beyond, we've got to say something
because people have lost their minds.
And I think that's why this team
of Yahoo reporters didn't have one
source or two sources or five sources.
They had 30 sources who all
confirmed each other's information.
Yeah, that is remarkable.
And I want to kind of talk about that
hierarchy for a second because it does
seem like it's a bit askew, right?
Because yes, in that case, the
CIA could be tamped down by the
NSC and basically like, no, we're
not doing that, that's ridiculous.
But at the same time, as Kevin Gosztola
points out in his book, there's a
good chance that Assange wouldn't be
facing the charges that he's facing
were it not for the CIA's rabid stance
against Assange, because the DOJ was
really scrambling to charge Assange
once Pompeo made it very clear that
he wanted Julian's head on a stick.
It seems like the hierarchy where
the CIA operates underneath anyone,
that doesn't seem to be the case.
Yeah, people, I think, generally
don't realize just how authoritative
the CIA is in areas of government
where they shouldn't even be a
part of the conversation, right?
The CIA's job, very simply, is
to recruit spies to steal secrets
and to analyze those secrets, to
allow policymakers to make the best
informed policy decisions, period.
That's it.
It shouldn't be up to the CIA to
decide who's charged with a crime,
who gets prosecuted with a crime,
to create paramilitary forces, to
carry out international kidnappings
or torture programs in archipelagos
of secret prisons, to decide what
Congress should and shouldn't know.
None of that should be up to the CIA,
but we've allowed the CIA, like we did
with the FBI in the 50s to just keep
pushing that envelope to the point
where it's too late to stop them.
And you need a Church Committee
or a Pike Committee to finally
reign them back in again.
Remember, Barack Obama, as bad as
he was, especially for national
security whistleblowers never
charged Julian Assange with a crime.
It was Donald Trump that did it.
Now, many of us, and I'll admit that I
was just as wrong as many of my friends
and colleagues, many of us thought
that, well, you know, Joe Biden was a
part of the Obama administration and he
knew what Obama was talking about when
he said that charging Assange would
give him a New York Times problem,
and we can certainly talk about that.
Certainly Biden understands the
New York Times problem and he'll
have to drop these charges.
No, he doubled down.
He doubled down and here we are, expecting
that Julian will be extradited to the
Eastern District before the end of this
year and then probably sit in pre trial
detention, you know, for years while the
two sides bicker about what should be
admitted as evidence and what shouldn't.
Yeah.
And I would definitely like you to
speak to the New York Times problem.
For people who don't know, could
you briefly explain what that is
before we, before we sign off?
Yeah, it's one of the funny
ironies of this whole situation.
You know, the Washington Post, the New
York Times, the Wall Street Journal, AP,
all of these big news outlets, these big
mainstream news outlets publish classified
information literally every single day.
Washington couldn't run if it didn't
have classified leaks every single day.
And usually it's the White House or
the Pentagon that's doing the leaking.
I can point to leaks that I'm positive
came from the CIA just in the last
two weeks about Israel / Palestine.
But when those leaks are authorized,
eh, you know, everybody's happy.
When the leaks are unauthorized, then
the White House is very upset and
the CIA will file something called
a Crimes Report with the FBI, and
then the FBI has to investigate it.
But the truth is, if you're going to
charge Julian Assange, a publisher
with multiple counts of espionage,
then you're going to have to charge the
Washington Post, the New York Times,
the Wall Street Journal, the L.A.
Times, AP, and everybody
else who publishes classified
information every single day.
Well, that's a First
Amendment violation, isn't it?
So we're either going to be transparent
and supporters of freedom of speech
and freedom of press, etc or we're not.
Because you can't be both.
Yeah, there really is that much that
hangs on this case, and I'm curious, just
because when you were speaking, I was
like, an authorized leak, wouldn't you
just call that sharing information, but
they still call it an authorized leak?
An authorized leak is like, the
CIA leaks: we got it right on Gaza.
We predicted three days before that
they were going to launch this attack.
And then they leak that to the Post
and then the Post says: classified
CIA paper says the CIA got it right.
And then the CIA says, Oh, no,
that information was classified.
It makes us look really good.
We probably should report it to the FBI.
But they probably won't be able to
figure out who leaked it anyway.
That's an authorized leak.
I see.
Okay.
Like accidentally posting a
really good looking picture of
yourself online or something.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Wow.
Okay.
John, thank you so much for giving
this really, really important
context and sharing your own
story about what happened to you.
Really appreciate it.
Oh, thanks for the work
that you do, Eleanor.
It's important.
Thanks for having me.
If you enjoyed the show, please
consider supporting our work
at Patreon.com/ProjectCensored